<DevelopmentPlan VERSION="0.2.0">
  <ArchitectureNotes>
    <objective>MINT replicates Claude's document generation pipeline as a standalone, model-agnostic toolkit. Plan optimizes for G0→G1→G2→G5→G6 minimum viable launch path. Phase 4 adds modular generation: decompose document into sections, generate each independently, assemble deterministically.</objective>
    <non-goal>No Claude API, no dvejsada dependency, no hosted SaaS, no macros/signatures/protection in v0.x.</non-goal>
    <risk-1>Frontier models may fail to produce valid docx-js/pptxgenjs code — G0 kill criterion. Mitigated by modular generation (Phase 4): smaller scope per call = higher success rate.</risk-1>
    <risk-2>Code execution sandbox security — restricted environment with no fs/net/timeout.</risk-2>
    <risk-3>Template engine must handle 7B model JSON reliably or G0 fails.</risk-3>
    <risk-4>Plan quality depends on model's ability to decompose user prompt into structured sections. Mitigated by plan validation + retry with plan refinement prompt.</risk-4>
    <architecture-pattern-1 name="Single-pass generation">M-CREATE → skill → model → sandbox → validate. Works for Claude-class models. 33% success on 35B.</architecture-pattern-1>
    <architecture-pattern-2 name="Modular generation">M-PLAN → M-SECTION[] → M-ASSEMBLE → validate. Each section is small enough for 35B. Plan is cheap JSON. Assembly is deterministic. ~90% success rate expected.</architecture-pattern-2>
    <architecture-pattern-3 name="Edit pipeline">M-EDIT receives a typed JSON EditPlan, not raw OOXML. M-OOXML unpacks/repacks the container; M-EDIT applies typed operations over the lxml tree. Tracked changes and comments follow ECMA-376; reply linkage lives in word/commentsExtended.xml.</architecture-pattern-3>
    <architecture-pattern-4 name="Dual Runtime Strategy">Python execution engine (mint.sdk + python-docx + RestrictedPython) replaces Node.js sandbox as the strategic default from v0.3. M-EDIT, M-GRACE, M-VALIDATE, M-FIX, M-OOXML are already pure Python. The change affects M-SANDBOX → MP-EXEC-FRONTIER, M-CREATE single-pass / M-ASSEMBLE / M-SECTION → mint_python.sdk. Node.js sandbox remains as optional fallback for legacy code paths via feature flag MINT_ENGINE=js.</architecture-pattern-4>
    <followup-1 name="M-GRACE on M-OOXML">M-GRACE currently maintains its own zip + Custom XML Parts logic. Once M-OOXML lands, M-GRACE should be refactored to use M-OOXML.unpack/pack so the round-trip and auto-repair invariants apply uniformly. Tracked as a Phase-5+ follow-up wave; not blocking for the Edit pipeline.</followup-1>
  </ArchitectureNotes>

  <Modules>
    <!-- ... rest of the file unchanged ... -->
  </Modules>
</DevelopmentPlan>